<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Akash Agrawal]]></title>
  <link href="http://akagr.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://akagr.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-16T11:33:27+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://akagr.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Akash  Agrawal]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Finally gonna date node.js]]></title>
    <link href="http://akagr.github.io/blog/2013/12/13/finally-gonna-date-node-dot-js/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-13T17:51:17+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://akagr.github.io/blog/2013/12/13/finally-gonna-date-node-dot-js</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I first heard of node.js, I was in graduation just getting into rails. But I seriously took notice when it displaced rails as the most popular repo on github. Speed whore as I am, I found event-driven non-blocking I/O particularly seducing.</p>

<p>I knew some elementary javascript and even at my work-ex of 7 months, never really used pure js. So I guessed, that just like ruby, I will definitely need to learn javascript a little. The world will be written in javascript in near future. Might as well start speaking it now.</p>

<p>That said, my javascript is still quite rusty. But at least I now understand how to utilize functions as closures and decided to return to node. Being a web-dev, obviously I can&rsquo;t be playing with vanilla quite long. After saying hello to a couple of worlds and writing my own servers with some routes thrown in for taste, meteor caught my eye.</p>

<p>About the only downside I can think of it is is that it does not have eyes for anything other than MongoDb. So I can&rsquo;t just start writing code for my projects.</p>

<p>A nodejs project should be coming my way in sometime. I am hopeful of that. I will be spending as much time as I can manage with node till then. Should be an interesting journey.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Riak: Installation on Ubuntu 12.04]]></title>
    <link href="http://akagr.github.io/blog/2013/12/11/riak-installation-on-ubuntu-12-dot-04/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-11T17:47:38+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://akagr.github.io/blog/2013/12/11/riak-installation-on-ubuntu-12-dot-04</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Riak is a relatively new kid on the block of NoSQL territory. It is based on principles of high availability, fault-tolerance, automatic replication and load balancing. Sounds like a deal for your next project&hellip; right? I got interested in one of my co-worker&rsquo;s project which is based on riak and decided to take it for a spin. Here is my first account with riak where I installed it on my Ubuntu 12.04 precise.</p>

<p>First I needed to get all the prerequisites right. This involves some packages and erlang. Now I already got error with erlang OTP R14 so I decided to go with the latest R16 (B02 to be exact).</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'>sudo apt-get install git build-essential libncurses5-dev openssl <span class="se">\</span>
</span><span class='line'>libssl-dev libssl0.9.8 libc6-dev libc6-dev
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Now download the latest erlang release from <a href="https://www.erlang-solutions.com/downloads/download-erlang-otp">here</a> and set it up as:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'>sudo dpkg -i &lt;your_downloaded_file.deb&gt;
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>If that goes suuccessfully and without a fuss, chances are that you will have a fully functioning riak installation in a jiffy.
Next steps are fairly simple.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'>git clone https://github.com/basho/riak.git
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">cd </span>riak
</span><span class='line'>make devrel
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Successful completion of the above indicates you&rsquo;re good. Just in case, let&rsquo;s check our installation.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nb">cd </span>dev
</span><span class='line'>dev1/bin/riak start
</span><span class='line'>dev1/bin/riak ping
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>If the output goes pong, you are all set to get your explorer cap on.</p>

<p>In my case, there were lots of head-scratching due to incompatibilities between erlang, riak sources yada yada. Hopefully the process goes smoothly for you. Hoot off below if you are having problems</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
